<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foundation of the faythfull In a sermon deliuered at Paules Crosse the 17. of Ianuarie. 1610. By Samuel Gardiner, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11577</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851764</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13700)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1098:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foundation of the faythfull In a sermon deliuered at Paules Crosse the 17. of Ianuarie. 1610. By Samuel Gardiner, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W.W[hite] for T. Manne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E (-E7,8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Copy catalogued does not contain extra leaf signed A1, with dedication to Archbishop G. Abbot in preface.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177637:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177637:1"/>
            <p>THE FOVNDATION <hi>of the Faythfull.</hi> In a Sermon deliuered at Paules Croſſe the 17. of Ianuarie. 1610. By SAMVEL GARDINER, Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Tim. 2.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Foundation of the Lord remayneth ſure, and hath this ſeale; The Lord knoweth who are his: And let euery one that calleth vpon the Name of the Lord, depart from Iniquitie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>W.W.</hi> for <hi>T. Manne.</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:177637:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177637:2"/>
            <head>The Foundation of the Faythfull.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. Tim. 2.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The foundation of the Lord remayneth ſure, and hath this ſeale; The Lord knoweth who are his: And let euery one that calleth vpon the Name of the Lord, depart from Iniquitie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE eſtate of Mans life, chiefely of the Chriſtians, holdeth compariſon tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout with the Seafa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring condition: So the writer to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuateth our Fayth,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.19.</note> which is the hand that holdeth vp our head, while we are floating ouer the Sea of this world, being ſirnamed by him, <hi>The Ancre of the Soule.</hi> The World is this ebbing and flowing Sea, in the ſucceſsiue ſurges thereof very much vnquiet: Mankind, while we heere liue, are the Saylers on this Sea, by ſirtes, by ſandes, by diuers dreadfull dangers.
<pb facs="tcp:177637:3"/>The Key-ſide or Shore, from whence we launch into the Maine, is our Birth into this world. The Port and Landing place to which we driue, is the Land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, the life that is to come. The whole Time ſpent from our Birth. to our Death, is our Seafaring ſeaſon. Our Shipmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, is our Sauiour; who by his Word and Spirit, ſaueth the Church, which is his Shippe, from perill of drowning, leading it ſafely to the Hauen of happineſſe.</p>
               <p>Now, heere the Apoſtle would haue vs edific our ſelues is this holy Fayth, and to build vpon this, as on a ſure foundation; that howſoeuer wee finde our ſelues throwne (as it were) into the midſt of this Sea, and that all the contrary Waues and Windes bende and bande themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs; corporally by croſſes, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by our ſinnes, by the feind, and the fleſh, inflicted vpon vs, that we cannot miſcarrie: But that we ſhall arriue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily at the Hauen of Heauen, aſwell in reſpect of the Decree of God eternall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uariable: as in regard of Chriſt, the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the cordage and tackle; whom Windes and Waues are forced to obey, as the Seruant his Maiſter.</p>
               <p>The ſumme and iſſue of theſe words, is this: That the ſtate of our ſaluation is ſure, as ſeated vpon the decree of God, a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb facs="tcp:177637:3"/>which is ſure: For our ſecuritie, a double Seale is ſette: 1. One in reſpect of God, with this Image &amp; ſuperſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> 2. The other touching our ſelues, with this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Ring &amp; Circle of it: <hi>Leteuery one that calleth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of Chriſt, depart, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Foundation of the Lord remaineth ſure.</hi> This <hi>Metophor,</hi> ſet vpon the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of the Text, is to haue applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the eternall counſaile of God touching our election, not by any oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite machination lyable to fruſtration. For it is of the nature of the foundation of an Houſe, whoſe vppermoſt ſtructure, and compoſition may be ſhaken; but the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſtandeth ſure. Foundations of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſort and condition layde by Mens hands, remaine ſure a long ſeaſon: Moſt ſure therefore muſt that Foundation bee, whoſe builder and maker is God. Now ſuch is the foundation of our Election, it is vpon the holy Hilles, vpon the Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> (which is Gods hill,) which cannot be remooued, but ſtandeth faſt for euer.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee are built vpon the Foundation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets &amp; Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe being the chiefe Corner-ſtone, Jn whom all the building coupled together, groweth vnto an holy Temple vnto the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Schoole of <hi>Rome</hi> would teach vs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe;
<pb facs="tcp:177637:4"/>Namely, That God his predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is chaungeable; and that hee that is predeſtinated, is contingently, or caſually predeſtinated; that is, by hap-hazard, or chaunce-medly, as we may ſo ſay. A Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition naturally begetting very ſtrange concluſions, as, That hee that is ordained vnto life, may be damned: And that hee that is determined to Damnation, may be ſaued. Which is nothing elſe, but of a ſure, to make an vnſure Foundation, &amp; to turne it vpſide downe. But wee haue not ſo learned Chriſt, but beleeue as hee hath taught vs by the mouth of his Prophets euer ſince the World beganne, that hee whoſe name is once noted in Gods Booke, and ſet downe in the writinges of the houſe of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> is written downe, neuer to be wiped out, and is ſeated vpon an euer enduring Foundation. This is the reaſon of this illation of our Sauiour:
<note place="margin">Math. 24.24.</note> 
                  <hi>If it were poſſible the very Elect ſhould bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</hi> This <hi>If,</hi> excluding all meanes of poſſibilitie of preiudicing the ſetled eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of the Elect. But the cauſe of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible matter of the ſeducement of the Elect, Totally and Finally layeth, in the courſe that God hath taken for them, of their continuance in the faith; for which cauſe elſe where hee ſaieth,
<note place="margin">Math. 25.34.</note> 
                  <hi>That a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is prepared for vs, from the beginning of
<pb facs="tcp:177637:4"/>the World:</hi> that wee might aſcertaine our ſelues, that when the time commeth, wee ſhall be abſolute owners and poſſeſſors of that Kingdome. Hence is it, that hee would haue vs ſhake off the feare, that misfaſhioned Fancie feedeth on:
<note place="margin">Luke. 12.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare not little Flocke, for it is your Fathers pleaſure to giue you the Kingdome.</hi> Wherefore it is, that we heare of this ioy and gladneſſe, that the boanes which our ſinnes haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, may reioyce: <hi>Reioyce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 10.20.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe your Names are written in heauen.</hi> Wherefore doth he tell vs, that our Names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe by the Finger of Gods hand, <hi>in Magna Charta,</hi> in the great Doomes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day booke of heauen? truely to make vs throughly perſwaded, that wee ſhall one day come to Heauen. But this, a luculent inſtance for the nonce, this ſolemne and ſerious aſſeueration of our Sauiour;
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.37.</note> 
                  <hi>All that the Father giueth mee,</hi> (that is, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Predeſtination in his minde) <hi>ſhall come to mee;</hi> (that is, by the ſteppes and feete of Fayth,) <hi>and him that commeth to me, I caſt not away.</hi> They come to Chriſt, who are giuen by Predeſtination by the Father vnto Chriſt; which is the cauſe they cannot become caſtawayes. Alſo, of his Sheepe, (that is to meane of his Elect) our Lord Ieſus ſpeaketh thus.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28.</note> 
                  <hi>I giue vnto them eternall life, &amp; they ſhall neuer
<pb facs="tcp:177637:5"/>periſh, neither ſhall any plucke them out of mine handes.</hi> The reaſon thereof followeth: <hi>My Father which gaue them mee, is greater then all:</hi> But he gaue them by predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them. For then are all the Elect giuen vnto Chriſt to be gouerned and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, when God hath choſen vs in Chriſt as in the head, to whom it neceſſarily belongeth to ſaue the ioyntes of his body. Sutable hereto is this his other ſaying; <hi>Thoſe that thou gaueſt me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.12.</note> 
                  <hi>haue I kept, and none of them is loſt, but the child of perdition.</hi> Where hee teacheth, that the Elect were truely giuen him of his Father; ſo that none of the Apoſtles, except <hi>Iudas,</hi> was loſt, becauſe he was ſo preordinated to be loſt. Whoſoeuer therefore are truely gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to Chriſt by the Father, they are in ſuch ſafe protection vnder Chriſt, as they cannot periſh; becauſe they are Elected; that is,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 13.18.</note> giuen to Chriſt. Elſewhere fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling vs, that one of the Colledge of Apoſtles, ſhould betray him, he prefaceth to the poynt in hand, in this wiſe: <hi>I ſpeake not of you all: J know whom J haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: but it is that the Scripture might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled; Hee that eateth bread with me, hath lift vp his heele againſt mee:</hi> Hee giueth the cauſe to Gods eternall Election, that none of the Apoſtles was to admit ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious ſinne of prodition; but onely
<pb facs="tcp:177637:5"/>
                  <hi>Iudas,</hi> as propoſed to perdition. Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing heard Chriſt him ſelfe ſpeaking for vs, what need wee more witneſſes?
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> Yet wee pleaſe to heare what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> can ſay for vs. In his golden Chaine twined with his foure indiuiduall linckes, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> is proclaymed at the Standard; therewithall, <hi>Called, Iuſtified, Glorified.</hi> And hee is in his expoſtulatorie Scrutinie, &amp; Inquirie, after him that dare ſtand out aduerſarie to this his poſitiue Diuinitie; <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect: It is God that Iuſtifieth, who ſhall condemne?</hi> As if he ſhould haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted it thus: They are Elected; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can they not be Condemned. Yea he prouoketh the proudeſt Enimie to the field for the triall of this trueth, as <hi>Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Tribulation,</hi> and all the vnited forces of <hi>Temptations;</hi> telling vs, how theſe when they haue done their worſt, can neuer be of power to raiſe our Foundation, and to ſunder vs from Chriſt. Laſtly, he would haue vs beleeue this, as a ſure word of prophecie, that neither Angels, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, or Powers, future, nor preſent thinges; altitudes or deapthes, nor any thing elſe, from the Center to the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, can vndoe this Foundation of our eternall and infallible Election. Deſtroy this Foundation, and all theſe
<pb facs="tcp:177637:6"/>rowes of ſpirituall Stones layde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, muſt needs come tumbling downe. As this ſaying of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Being iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Fayth, wee haue Peace towards God:</hi> Which peace of conſcience towards God, we can not haue, ſo long as we hoouer (as the Rauen,) betweene Heauen and Earth, and are in perplexitie about our Election. As this other his ghoſtly Aphoriſme, <hi>Fayth maketh not aſhamed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe the loue of God is ſhed abroad in our heartes by the holy Ghoſt, which is giuen vs;</hi> If fully, and finally, this loue may be loſt of vs, whereby we are couered with ſhame and confuſion as it were with a Cloake. As this his other peece of Lecture:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſpirit of God witneſſeth with our ſpirit, that we are the children of God:</hi> So be it that wee yeeld that the Spirit may be quite extinguiſhed in vs. It is Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> aſſertion,
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.19.</note> and the marke indeed of thoſe of reprobate condition: <hi>They went from vs, but they were not of vs: for if they had been of vs, they ſhould haue continued with vs:</hi> For it is flatte which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>The giftes and calling of God are without repentance;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> and ſo by courſe of conſequence, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not repent that he hath predeſtinated vs. Thus doe our Popelinges fall before the Scriptures, as <hi>Dagon</hi> before the Arke; and the foundation of our Election ſtandeth ſure.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177637:6"/>
               <p>And now we will deale with them by dinte, and force of reaſon; and thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute for the ſoliditie of this our Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, <hi>a poſteriorj,</hi> Gods purpoſe to ſaue the Elect in this world, is abſolutly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: Therefore he ſo Calleth, Iuſtifieth, Regenerateth them, ſo qualifieth them with the Induments and Ornaments of his ſpirit, ſo gouerneth them, and giueth them the guift of perſeuerance, as he neuer repenteth himſelfe of theſe collated bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, inasmuch as repentance cannot fall vpon him, as Scripture before taught vs. God followeth his choſen with an indiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall, vnweariſome, and eternall loue; So ſayeth God in <hi>Jeremie:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 31.3.</note> 
                  <hi>J haue loued thee with an euerlaſting loue.</hi> So ſayeth Chriſt in <hi>John: For as much as he loued his owne which were in the world, vnto the end he loued them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 13 1.</note> But he willeth and worketh nothing now, which was not willed and determined by him from all eternitie: wherfore this foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of abſolute ſtabilitie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>A priorj,</hi> we pleade thus; Election is only in God, and not in man, in as much as Election was before the Creation, and ſo before man:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee were choſen</hi> (ſaieth the Apoſtle) <hi>before the worlds foundation.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if Eection be a part of diuine Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and Prouidence is Gods: the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb facs="tcp:177637:7"/>is naturall, that Election muſt be in God, and no part thereof may cleaue to mans thumbes. And hence alſo the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction is as needfull, that it is eternall and immutable, as conſiſting in God onely; in whom all thinges are according to his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without variableneſſe or ſhaddow of change. Stood the Foundation of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection vpon no ſurer ground then Man, it would ſoone be turned vp: For <hi>Euripus</hi> changeth not oftner then Man. And what may Man doe ſimply by himſelfe towards his owne ſaluation? He that is a reprobate, can lay to himſelfe a ſure Foundation wherevpon he may build his owne dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; in aſmuch as not beeing ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupported by the hand of God, (God not beeing bounde vnto him thereunto) he ſimply can bring foorth nothing but fruites vnto death, with willfullneſſe enough; and ſo vndoe himſelfe: But Election cannot ſo bee made ſure of the part of the Elect, as by nature mutable, and as ſo continually and grieuouſly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: So, as ſo farre as it layeth in them, they quite ſtrip themſelues of the graces of God; and if doome ſhould be denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced according to their deedes, there were no foundation made for them in Heauen. The effects of Election are in the perſons themſelues that are elected, as their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:177637:7"/>paſſiue, and ſo their Iuſtification and regeneration in this ſenſe; alſo faith, and the workes of faith, and at laſt their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification in like manner. Wherefore theſe effects in vs that are of the Elect, admitte an alteration in reſpect of our ſelues: Wherevpon by nature, faith, and regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, may be loſt of vs; and of righteous, wee may become vnrighteous, and ſo fall from grace, and periſh. But in regard of predeſtination, and diuine decree which is in God, &amp; ſo immutable: it can not be, that theſe guiftes of God, and theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of Predeſtination ſhould be quite without effect; and therefore hauing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on God, our ſaluation is moſt ſafe. Haue a view heereof in the courſe of the world, led by the hand of heauenly prouidence. For <hi>Saeculum Speculum;</hi> The World is a Looking-glaſſe in this caſe: For how is it that it is ſo well ordered, ſo as the Heauens keepe their ſtations ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Sunne knoweth his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing, and the Moone her going downe; the alternall entercourſe of the day and the night is not to bee diſturbed, and all thinges execute their offices in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in their ſeuerall ranckes and claſſes, wherin they were firſt placed? It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Pouidence that vſshereth the World, is not in the Creature, no not in
<pb facs="tcp:177637:8"/>the hand of Man or of Angell; but in the ſole power of the vnchaunging God that holdeth the ball of the World in his hand; and ſo is vnchangeable. And hence is it that the execution of ſupreme proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in like ſort, &amp; all the effects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hold on ſo ſet and ſetled a tenor, and haue ſo good ſucceſſe. And heere follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the aſſurance of predeſtination, as founded vpon the certaine foundation of Gods eternall counſaile: Wherefore well ſaieth Saint <hi>Augustine, Turiores erimus ſi to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Deo demus.</hi> It ſhall be ſafeſt for vs to hold all in Capite, and to giue all to God. 3. Our next reaſon is of this faſhion. The decree of Election, as of Reprobation, is eternall; The Scriptures make this good: But whatſoeuer is eternall is inuariable, for wee call that Eternall, which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either beginning or ending, and not ſubiect vnto changing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Wee further vrge the preſent cauſe thus: Election is only in the will of God, and hath no copartner-ſhip with workes foreſeene either good or euill, (as in ſome ſort we will prooue towardes the end:) Now that which is independant of it ſelfe, &amp; hath no other proceeding then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the will of God, can by no other by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanes beſide God, be daſhed or made voyde. Now in God himſelfe, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:177637:8"/>at oddes with his Will; whereby it commeth to paſſe, that the Will which is in God, which we tearme the abſolute and the ſecret Will, is euermore the ſame.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Moreouer, we tender this argument vnto them; Election is not without fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge: For God hath foreknowne ſuch as ſhalbe ſaued: but Gods fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge is vnerring, and ſo ſure (as in the ſequell of this text we ſhall ſhew) and ſo the ſtate of our Election ſtandeth ſure.</p>
               <p n="6">6. I ſay further, (let them checke what is ſaid, if they can) that ſo many &amp; ſo maine are the meanes that are prepared and ſet out by God, for the common ſaluation of the Church, as they can not poſsibly paſſe the handes of God, but needes they muſt be ſaued.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Beſide all this, Gods Will is a worke,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.3.</note> as it is in <hi>Pſalmodie, Our God is in heauen; he hath done whatſoeuer it pleaſed him.</hi> But it is his flatte Will, the Elect ſhould be ſaued; it muſt therefore needes be ſo.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Adde hitherto, that he that tranſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Will, is ledde therevnto, either out of the proſpect to a better prouiſion, by a ſecond wiſedome; or out of the ſenſe of his inſufficiencie, for the execution of his primatiue intention: Wherefore there is no other ſhift, but when we can not what we would, we will what we can. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:177637:9"/>of theſe may be ſpoken of God; for being only wiſe, a better counſaile cannot be conceiued, then was firſt from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie conſidered of: And being omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, his armes as <hi>Sampſons,</hi> are not to be manacled; but whatſoeuer he proiecteth hee perfourmeth.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Finallie, all thinges worke to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to the worſt, through their owne wickedneſſe, yea the good things of God, as his grace, and the graces of his holy Spirit;
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.7. Luk. 2.3 4. 2. Cor. 2.16. Rom. 2.4. Gal. 5.13. 1. Cor. 11.27.</note> for Chriſt is to them <hi>A Rocke of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and a ſtone to stumble at, appointed for the ruine and fall of many.</hi> The Goſpell, <hi>is a ſauor of death, vnto death.</hi> The <hi>long ſufferance of God, that citeth them to repentance,</hi> through the iniurie they offer it, ſerueth to the enlargement of the hardeneſſe of their heartes; Their <hi>Chriſtian libertie,</hi> is to them an occaſion to liue licentiouſly.</p>
               <p>The Supper of the Lord, their ſpirituall refection, becommeth their poyſon. Wherfore, contrariwiſe, all things ſort out for the beſt to the elect, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; yea, their very ſinnes themſelues, as rightly <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth.</p>
               <p>To graunt a mutabilitie in God, is to bring in theſe abſurdities with a ſtrong hande, that Gods will may be chaunged: his foreknowledge deceiued: His illimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted power reſtrained: His action hindred;
<pb facs="tcp:177637:9"/>which to graunt, is to denie him to be God; for hee is a goodly God indeede, whoſe knowlede may be blemiſhed with errour, his will, with variableneſſe, his power, with weakeneſſe, his action, with fruſtration.</p>
               <p>But what ſay wee all this while to our ſinnes? do not theſe driue at the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and ſerue to vndermine it? truly, there is nothing that put ſo forcibly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto as they; So that name theſe, and name al,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32 33.</note> according to this denuntiation of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Who ſo euer haue ſinned againſt mee, J will put him out of my Booke:</hi> But bee yee not diſmaide: The hand of that Scripture, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Axe only at the roote of preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and malicious ſinnes, continued to the death;
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.6.</note> ſuch as is our obdurate rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt Chriſt, wrought in a very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe &amp; accompanied with a final impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence. Our daily falles, enforced through the infirmitie of the Fayth in vs, as beeing but in <hi>Herba, et non in Spica;</hi> In the Graſſe, and not in the Eare, in Inchoation &amp; not in Perfection, will not doe the deede. I denie not that our ſinnes deſerue ſo much, and that they draw out the ſword of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce out of the ſcabberd of his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to ſtrike vs both wayes, inwardly, and outwardly, as he dealt with <hi>Dauid:</hi> But withall, mindfull of his trueth and goodneſſe, and for the obedience ſake of
<pb facs="tcp:177637:10"/>his ſonne Chriſt, his decree of ſauing vs, which is our Foundation, is ſure on our ſide: for our ſinnes are cancelled; that is, they are not to death imputed. He endueth vs with Fayth &amp; Repentance, whereby we are rayſed &amp; ſet vpon our feete. The cauſe hereof is, for that as he hath choſen vs vnto life, ſo he hath withall miniſtred the meanes of Fayth, and Compunction, that bring vs vnto this life. Wherefore as we haue a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in our ſelues of Fayth, and conuerſion; ſo of our aſſured Predeſtination vnto Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, let vs make no further queſtion: For if our ſinnes, into which by ineuitable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of nature we were to fall, &amp; God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw the ſame, were not able to make ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of the courſe of Gods purpoſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinating vs to eternall life, in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, as a woorke of his free grace; ſurely after our his falles into them, this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, gratious, &amp; ſtedfaſt election, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be voided. By grace, our names had firſt enrolement in Gods regiſter; So by grace they there ſtand ſtill. I ſay further, becauſe wee are ſeparated to ſaluation; by Gods grace it is that we are kept from thoſe ſins of contumacie and impenitencie, for which the Reprobate (which were neuer there written,) are ſaid to haue the wipe-out of the Booke of life, when as what they are, by degrees they are manifeſted; that is to
<pb facs="tcp:177637:10"/>ſay, ſuch as neuer had been enrolled; <hi>Dauid</hi> neuer deſpaired of his recouerie, for his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie and murther: Nor <hi>Peter,</hi> for his tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble apoſtaſie, which hereby appeareth, in that amideſt all thoſe ſtormes of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they held faſt the Fayth, the Ancre of the Soule, and called vpon the Lord.</p>
               <p>Heere I would haue done with this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and haue buckled my ſelfe to the reſt of the Building, but that there are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections of Scriptures againſt vs, that are needfull to bee anſweared.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As this from <hi>Ezechiel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 18.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Jf the righteous turne away from his righteousneſse, and commiteth iniquitie: Jn the ſinnes that he hath ſinned, in them he ſhall die.</hi> This ſuppoſall <hi>If,</hi> is true: but where is it ſimply ſayd without an <hi>If,</hi> that the Righteous ſhall make this reuolt from his righteouſneſſe. <hi>If,</hi> is often in Scripture language, as to ſay, Not at all: As where it is ſayd, <hi>If a man ſhall keepe the Law, hee ſhall liue in his owne righteouſneſſe:</hi> where this <hi>If,</hi> is as much as, that which is impoſsible: Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions doe not ſet downe any thing; if they doe, an other thing is aymed at, then is there ſuppoſed. God is at ſuch deadly fewde with ſinne, as who ſo ſhall cherriſh it in his breaſt, ſhall feele his vengeance fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him at the backe: wherefore it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs to continue in well doing; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in the Spirit, wee end not in the
<pb facs="tcp:177637:11"/>Fleſh. If we doe, as we haue ſowen, we ſhall reape: Wee haue ſowen Sinne, wee ſhall reape Iuſtice.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.</note> An other is from that counſaile of Saint <hi>Paul, Thou ſtandeſt by faith: be not high minded, but feare.</hi> Wee anſwere, there arrogancie, &amp; ſupine ſecuritie is inhibited, and an holy feare and reuerence enioyned vs. Thoſe that are of the Foundation, can not be of this high minde and preſumption, as to ſhake off all feare, and to become altogether careleſſe, for ſo might the very Elect be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, to whom this <hi>Cautat</hi> is directed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. An other is from this warning of the ſame Apoſtle;
<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Quench not the Spirit.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that we find not the affirmatiue part, that the Spirit is quenched. I yeelde, that 1. Gods graces may miniſh in a man: To which purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.30.</note> theſe dictates, and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are deliuered vs, <hi>Quench not the Spirit. Grieue not the Spirit of God, by which ye are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the day of redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That the graces of God may be buried in a man, yea, for a time ſeeme dead, like a man in a traunce; as <hi>Eutychus</hi> was when hee fell from the third loft: Yet we may ſay of him,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.9.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> did of <hi>Eutychus. Trouble not your ſelues, for his life is in him.</hi> Whom we likewiſe hearten with this text out of <hi>Jſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 65.8.</note> 
                  <hi>The wine is found in the cluſter, and one ſaieth, destroy it not, for a bleſſing is in it.</hi> As alſo with this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
<pb facs="tcp:177637:11"/>of the ſame Prophet,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 6.13.</note> 
                  <hi>There is ſubſtance in the Elme, or in the Oake, when they cast their leaues.</hi> In which plight, ſtood <hi>Dauid</hi> in his adultrie: <hi>Peter</hi> in his apoſtaſie: <hi>Salomon</hi> in his Idolatrie.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That a man after repentance, may haue often relapſe, yet ſhall riſe againe; as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> when hee twice lyed, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> when he twice prophanely ſweared, as <hi>Dauid</hi> that fell often into adulteries, beſide other iniquities. If Man, that hath not a Mite of mercie reſpected with God, muſt ſeauentie times ſeauen forgiue his brother euery day, that treſpaſſeth againſt him: how may we faddome, &amp; comprehend Gods mercies, &amp; in what boundes may we containe them?</p>
               <p n="4">4 That a man may ſinne preſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is heynous and horrible; againſt which <hi>Dauid</hi> thus poureth foorth his ſpirit like water, before the Lord:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Keepe thy ſeruant from preſumptuous ſinnes, leaſt they get the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer mee; ſo ſhall I be vndefiled, and innocent from the great offence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Finally,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.7.</note> that a man may deſpaire of Gods mercie, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, where he play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it thus: <hi>Js his Mercie cleane gone for euer, and is his Promiſe come vtterly to an end for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more? And J ſayd, this is my death.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 6.2.3.6.</note> As <hi>Job</hi> did, where he thus bewrayeth it: <hi>Oh that my griefe were well weighed, and my miſeries were layde togeather in the ballance: For it would be
<pb facs="tcp:177637:12"/>now heauier then the Sand of the Sea; therefore my wordes are ſwallowed vp: For the Arrowes of the Almightie are in mee, the venome there of did drinke vp my ſpirit.</hi> And he further complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that God is turned enimie, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth bitter thinges againſt him, and ſetteth him vp for a Butte to ſhoote at. As the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous <hi>Corinthian</hi> almoſt did; for he was drouping and ſtooping that way,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.7.</note> but that <hi>Paul</hi> watched him, and charged the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> concerning him; <hi>Comfort him, leaſt he be ſwallowed vp with ouermuch heauineſſe.</hi> As <hi>Luther</hi> did for three yeares togeather after his conuerſion, by his owne confesſion. And as ſome among vs, haue done a longer time: Yea, Deſpaire may ſucke and ſoake the body, as much as any Sickneſſe.</p>
               <p>But the Spirit can not quite be extinct in the Elect: their Deſpaire ſhall be neither <hi>Totall,</hi> nor <hi>Finall:</hi> not <hi>Totall,</hi> becauſe this Deſpaire ſhall not be from the whole heart: For Fayth in that exigent, ſhall couet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Deſpaire. Not <hi>Finall,</hi> becauſe hee ſhall recouer himſelfe before the end of his life. In the meane while, it ſhalbe our partes, to cheriſh the ſparkes of the Spirit in our heartes, and eſchew ſuch meanes, as are the quenchment thereof. But they reaſon but abſurdly, who out of the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour that muſt be ours of preſeruing of the Spirit, would conclude, the danger
<pb facs="tcp:177637:12"/>wee are in, of quite quenching it: For the meaning of the Apoſtle in that place, is onely this; That wee be not too indulgent to the Fleſh, in the fight againſt the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="3">3 An other obiection is from the ſixt to the <hi>Hebrewes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.4, 5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Jt is impoſſible that they which were once lightned, and haue taſted of the Heauenly guiftes, &amp;c. If they fall away, ſhould be renued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by repentance.</hi> whereunto wee put in this our double anſwere. 1. Firſt, that there it is not ſaide, that ſuch at any time fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. 2. Secondly, that many Reprobates haue this illumination, but without ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, yet with ſome cheere and chaunge of affections, ſuch as was in <hi>Saule, Iudas, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> and in thoſe of the Parable, who receiued the ſeede of the worde with ioy, but ſuffred it not to roote; and that ſuch fall for a full due, it is both certaine, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie: But this is nothing to the Elect, who after all their fallinges, haue againe their happie riſings: Their faith being ſeconded with a <hi>Corroborating, and ſtrengthning grace of perſeuerance to the end.</hi> And this is that grace that <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhed the <hi>Epheſians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>That they may be ſtrengthned by his ſpirit in the inner-man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.11.</note> And to the <hi>Coloſians, that they may be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with all might, through his glorious power.</hi> The grace which he felt in himſelfe, where he ſayeth, <hi>J am able to doe all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>through the helpe of Christ, that ſtrengthneth me.</hi> The grace
<pb facs="tcp:177637:13"/>that God giueth all ſuch as feare him, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that the royall Prophet ſayeth, <hi>He ſhall make them strong,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and lusty like an Eagle.</hi> This grace is ours in a double reſpect. 1. Of the promiſe of God in <hi>Jeremie, J will put my feare in their heartes, that they ſhall neuer depart from mee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 22.32.</note> 2. Of the Prayer of Chriſt, <hi>J haue prayed for thee, that thy ſayth ſhould not fuile thee.</hi> Hetherto maketh this ſweete ſpeech of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De corrept. et gratia. cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Ipſe cos facit in bono perſeuerare, quj facit bonos.</hi> He that maketh men good, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men to continue good; and hee allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that loue that may be loſt; wherfore hee ſayeth, <hi>Charitas quae deſerj poteſt, nunquam vera fuit.</hi> That Charitie that may be caſſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red is but counterfaite.</p>
               <p n="4">4 An other Obiection is from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſuch as haue departed from the Fayth,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4, 1. Theſ. 1.4. 1. Pet. 1.1.</note> as the <hi>Epheſians, Theſsalonians,</hi> and diſpearſed <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſtyled in holy Writinges, <hi>The elect and choſen,</hi> whereas many of them did afterward forſake their firſt Loue, and gaue vp their Fayth as it were in the plaine field. Heereto we anſwere, that there are two ſortes of Iudgementes touching mans eſtate this way. 1. The one is called <hi>Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium Certuudinis,</hi> the Iudgement of Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; by which an vndoubted doome may be deliuered of any mans Election. But that is Gods royaltie, peculiar to himſelfe, ſette downe in his ſacred, and ſecret booke of
<pb facs="tcp:177637:13"/>counſailes; man is not to meddle with it, no further then God hath reuealed to one man, an othermans eſtate. 2. The other is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Judicium Charitatis.</hi> The Iudgement of Charitie; whereby wee proceede by the Lawe of Loue, eſteeming of ſuch as liue in the Church, and outwardly beare loue to the word of truth, to be in the Calender of the Choſen, vntill wee haue a better Schoolemaiſter then Nature, to informe vs the contrarie. Now in reſpect theſe <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Theſsalonians,</hi> and <hi>Iewes,</hi> did beare theſe outward markes; the Apoſtle maketh the beſt conſtruction of their doinges, as Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie would haue him. 2. Againe, they may be deemed to be thus denominated, <hi>a maiorj parte,</hi> of the greateſt part, according to the common courſe of ſpeach, wherby we call it an Heape of Corne, which ſtandeth moſt vpon the Corne, though much confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with colder, and with chaffe.</p>
               <p n="5">5 An other Obiection,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.11.</note> is this admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Saint <hi>John</hi> giueth: <hi>Hold that which thou haſt, that no man take thy Crowne:</hi> whereby is meant (as ſome would haue it) <hi>The Crowne of heauenly glory:</hi> Whereto they inferre this <hi>Prouiſo</hi> of the Apoſtle;
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leaſt he fall.</hi> We anſwere, that the Crowne there mentioned, is the Crowne of the Miniſtrie; which without loſſe to our election, may be loſt, and can
<pb facs="tcp:177637:14"/>not be rightly taken for the Crowne of heauenly glorie. And what if it could, &amp; we ſhould graunt ſo much; there would be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing gotten by it? For it is to be conceiued, that one of theſe two wayes, it is to be loſt. 1. Either in reſpect of our ſelues. 2. Or of God. 1. In reſpect of our ſelues, wee eaſily yeelde it, that wee may ſoone looſe this Crowne from our heads: For we are fickle and feeble, &amp; nothing elſe but a compound of corruption.</p>
               <p>Now Death, and not the Diademe of Glorie, is the debt that is due to Sinne. 2. But in reſpect of God, who hath choſen vs; and of Chriſt, in whom wee are choſen, this Crowne can neuer be taken away from vs, in aſmuch as the giftes and vocation of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> are without reuerſion. Wherefore in both theſe reſpectes, wee haue warning in the Scriptures to looke to our ſtanding, and to tread ſure, leaſt wee fall. And are taught herewithall, that the Elect ſtand ſure in the Sanctuarie of the Lord, they are vnder the ſafe protection of Chriſt, and ſo can not periſh.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The laſt Obiection I will deale with, is from ſuch places of Scripture, as ſpeake of Blotting out of the Booke of life: As that peece of Imprecation of <hi>Dauids</hi> againſt his Enimies:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Let them be wiped out of the Booke of the Liuing, and not be written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:177637:14"/>the Righteous.</hi> As that aſſeueration of the Spirit in the <hi>Apocalips:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>He that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth, I will not put out his name out of the Booke of Life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 32.32. Rom. 9.3.</note> As thoſe paſsionate wiſhes of <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul,</hi> to be put out of the writinges of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the people of God committed to their charge. All which places conclude nothing leſſe, then that they make ſhew of at the firſt ſight, being not throughly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. <hi>Dauids</hi> enemies had neuer any name in Gods booke, but only in the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious opinion of the Church. And therefore it can not properly be ſayd of them, that they were ſpunged out: But in Scripture phraſe, they are taken ſo to be, when their hypocriſie is diſcouered, and they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted what they are. So <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth thoſe wordes of the <hi>Pſalme: Let them be wiped out of the Booke of the Liuing;</hi> that is, <hi>Scriptjnon eſse cognoſcantur tam ab ipſis, quam ab alijs;</hi> Let it appeare both to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and others, that they are not written downe. They ſeeme to be written (ſayth the ſame Father) <hi>Secundum praeſentem Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, et temporariam fidem,</hi> as they carry cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite in the World, for their good carriage of themſelues in their outward actions, and for their temporarie profeſsion. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Moſes</hi> his wiſh; ſome thereby would meane the Booke of this preſent life, as if
<pb facs="tcp:177637:15"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould deſire to dye for his People: As if he ſhould haue ſaide, Eyther ſaue them, or ſlay mee. But this meaning is too light to ſuite with the grauitie of this his petition. For many Captaines and Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunts haue been founde, that haue been prodigall of their owne, for the ſafeguard of their Souldiers liues: And it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement the Godly ſtande charged with, to giue their liues for their Brethren. Wherein <hi>Moſes</hi> had had his matches euen among the Heathens, ſuch as were <hi>Philenj</hi> that were brethren, <hi>Decius, Curtius, Theſeus,</hi> and ſuch like, that made no ſpare of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of their blood, for the benefite of their Countrie: Wherefore ſome giue theſe wordes to the Booke of the Couenant, as if he ſhould haue ſayd, Blot my Name out of thy Church-booke, and let it no more be in the number of thoſe to whom thou haſt made thy Promiſes of eternall life. Not that <hi>Moſes</hi> deſired directly to be damned for the peoples deliueraunce, but onely to be excommunicate from the Church, that is heere on earth; which is ſomewhat more then to die.</p>
               <p>But ſome of better iudgement then the the former, are of the minde, that <hi>Moſes</hi> loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked higher then ſo; namely to the Booke of eternall life; as if he ſhould thus ſay: Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then thy whole people ſhould periſh,
<pb facs="tcp:177637:15"/>let my name no more ſtand in thy Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-booke, in the number of thoſe whom thou haſt put apart to eternall life. And becauſe this Expoſition ſeemeth to breed, and to bring ſome abſurdities with it (as that ſo great a man ſhould make a motion of a thing impoſsible; his Predeſtination in the certificate of his owne knowledge beeing not to be altered; as alſo that hee ſhould deſire that which is vnlawfull, to be raced out of the Regiſter of the Righteous: which is to change copie, and to turne enemie vnto God,) they put in this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder, that the Prophet rauiſhed in zeale of affections to the glory of God, and the good of the people, was ſomewhat beſide himſelfe, and ſpake he knew not what.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe they conſider of Saint <hi>Paules</hi> vow, to be ſundred from Chriſt, for his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, his Kinſmen according to the fleſh: And it is incident as wee know to theſe paſsionate affections, as heeding only that, vpon which their minde is bent, not to heed themſelues. This is the verdite of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great men, whoſe authoritie wee are iuſtly to reuerence. But to vnbowell our thoughts in the caſe, howſoeuer we may yeeld them what they ſay concerning <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> inasmuch as his parley with God, was extemporall, and familiar, and wee may note him of ſome raſhneſſe: That wee
<pb facs="tcp:177637:16"/>ſhould marke out Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for ſuch a man, and make him of this humour, is more I am perſwaded, then that place will ſuffer. For <hi>Paul</hi> wrote it, and not worded it; his hand ledde the Penne, &amp; the Spirit led his heart, as his ſolemne preamble into that matter witneſſeth,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.1.</note> in this forme of conteſtation, <hi>I ſay the truth in Chriſt, and lye not, my conſcience bearing me witneſse in the Holy-ghoſt.</hi> This pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall prouocation and appellation of the Apoſtle, is argument of perſwaſion ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient vnto vs, that mature deliberation, and not precipitate affection wrought this reſolution. And in that the Spirit ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted it, it cannot be excepted againſt.</p>
               <p>Againe, we diſtinguiſh of the nature and manner of his vow, as there is a ſeparation from the loue of Chriſt: And as there is a priuation of the fruites of his loue. That <hi>Paul</hi> did wiſh the firſt to bid Chriſt adiew, and to be execrable for his Breathren, it is not, nay ought not to be ſuppoſed; For that flatly croſſeth the concluſion of the Chapter before, touching his inſeparable ſocietie with Chriſt; and it checketh the principall cauſe of the very Vow it ſelfe; which was not ſo much his loue to his Brethren, as his loue to Chriſt; whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hee thought in the repudiation of the people, ſhould not be litle hazarded, as to whom appertained the Adoption, and the
<pb facs="tcp:177637:16"/>Glorie; the Couenant, and the Law; the Worſhip of God, and Promiſes: and of whom came Chriſt according to the fleſh. For hee ſaw what the World would gather vpon it, if God ſhould roote out the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas,</hi> and plant the Nations: namely, that either God ſtood not to his Promiſe; or that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was not that <hi>Meſsiah</hi> promiſed. This was that which pricked <hi>Paul</hi> in the quickeſt Vaine, and ſtabbed him at the Heart. Yet did his inwarde Bowels bleede in affections to his Brethren, condoleing their deſtruction. But Chriſt and his glory, put them to the vttermoſt ſtraint that might be. Wherefore while hee is in this Feruour of loue, and his affections are thus flagrant towardes Chriſt, it is not without reaſon to thinke that in compunction to his kinne, hee could wiſh to be cut off from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Chriſt. But wee take it that wee are in the right, in expounding his Wiſh of the fruites of Chriſtes loue, as the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the faythfull in the life eternall, of which he would be depriued, and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to damnation, rather then his eyes ſhould behold the expunction of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of the Couenant of Grace, to the great obloquie &amp; reproach of Gods name, and of his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus. And this fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth well the ſpirit of that loue that he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth towards Chriſt. And this is the Gloſſe
<pb facs="tcp:177637:17"/>of <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> on this text.</p>
               <p>Neyther doubt we at all, but that the ſame Spirit was with <hi>Moſes</hi> his tongue, which was with <hi>Pauls</hi> Pen; that the one ſpake, the other wrote with aduiſement enough, the ſame cauſe, the extent of their loue to the glorie of God, and the indemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their People, working theſe affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wiſhes in them. Wherefore both theſe obiections of examples, receiue the ſame anſwere: As if <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould haue ſaide in this maner. O be gratious vnto thy People, not only for their owne ſaluation ſake, but for the glorie of thy name; or if thine hand muſt needs take hold on Iudgement, let their blood be vpon my head, and let mee goe downe vnto the damned. Neither doth this imprecation of his, ſtrike at all at the Foundation of Gods vnchaungeable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of election, the ſame implying in it a tacite condition, if it were poſsible. But hee knew it, that it was abſolutely impoſsible. As Chriſt when he did deprecate the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueall of the Cuppe, which he knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not be remooued, <hi>Father, if it be poſſible, let this Cuppe paſse from mee.</hi> The ſhort ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me therefore of <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſuite is this, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blotte mee (if it may bee) out of thy Booke of life, then that thy People ſhould be deſtroyed, and thy name blaſphemed; all which maketh nothing to the purpoſe, to
<pb facs="tcp:177637:17"/>prooue that thoſe that are penned downe in that Booke, may be afterward put out. </p>
               <trailer>And thus much ſhall ſuffice for the forepart of this Text.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>It followeth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>And hath this Seale; The Lord knoweth who are his.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>By an other fitte Metaphor, hee conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, the certaine ſaluation of the elect, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the auntient cuſtome of men, ſetting their Signets and ſealing Rings, to that which they minde to ratifie. God ſigned the promiſes of temporall deliueraunces, made vnto his people with his gracious ſeale. A Seale was ſet vpon <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Family, that the Deluge ſhould not drowne them. <hi>Sodome</hi> was not ſentenced to combuſtion, before <hi>Loth,</hi> and his Family, were marked out to an happie preſeruation. In the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted puniſhment vpon the firſt borne of <hi>Egipt,</hi> the aſperſion of the Blood of the Lambe vpon the Lintels and Dore-poſtes of the houſes of the <hi>Jſraelites,</hi> was the Lords Broad ſeale and Charter, of their immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from the common ſlaughter. Whereas ſixe Angels in <hi>Ezechiel</hi> were diſpached by God, againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> for their deſtruction:
<note place="margin">Ezech. 9.</note> An other Angell apparelled in white, (with an Incke-horne at his Girdle,) was <hi>Legatus a Latere,</hi> ſent on this Legatiue errant, to ſaue ſuch, as ſhould be ſealed with the letter <hi>Tau,</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fore-heads, as theire paſport, and
<pb facs="tcp:177637:18"/>protection: Much more is our ſpirituall deliuerance aſſured vs, by ſignes and ſeales of it. There is no man elected vnto eternall life, but ſhal be ſealed at the time appointed. And this is that ſealing which is ſo often mentioned in the Scriptures; as where in the Reuelation it is ſayd,
<note place="margin">Apo. 7.4.8.</note> that a number without number, was ſealed vnto the Lord. For like as the Father hath ſealed Ieſus Chriſt as he was Man,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> and Mediator with the holy Ghoſt aboue his fellowes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe; <hi>Him hath, God the Father ſealed:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> So alſo the reſt of his Children he hath ſealed, &amp; doth dayly ſeale with Markes and Characters of their certaine Election, to deuide them from the outcaſtes of this preſent euill world.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.21.</note> As where he ſayth: <hi>who hath ſealed vs, and giuen vs the earneſt of the ſpirit.</hi> And in the latter to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> thus:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>After that yee beleeued, ye were ſealed with the holy ſpirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.30.</note> And in the ſame Epiſtle thus: <hi>Grieus not the holy Spirit of God, by whom yee are ſealed vnto the day of Redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Seales are the Meanes to ſerue the end ſette downe by God. Predeſtination is not onely of the Ende, but alſo of the Meanes that make to that end. Now all of them aſwell the Ende, as the meanes, are the Effectes thereof. Wherefore rightly ſayth <hi>Auguſtine: Praedeſtinatio est praeparatio bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiorum
<pb facs="tcp:177637:18"/>Dej, quibus certiſſimè liberantur qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> liberantur:</hi> Predeſtination is a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue of the graces of God, by which they are moſt aſſuredly ſaued, who are to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <p>Theſe Meanes, in ſome are more impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, in ſome more eminent in ſome more, in ſome leſſe: Some haue but a litle Oyle in their Cruiſe: In ſome, their cuppe doe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowe. Thoſe meanes are our Vocation, Iuſtification, Sanctification, Repentaunce, new Obedience; without which; there is no entraunce to the Throne of Grace: But by theſe Groomes, wee may be brought into the Kinges Chamber.</p>
               <p>Heere the two principall Seales and Meanes, are ſet out vnto vs: as <hi>Fayth,</hi> and <hi>New obedience:</hi> the naturall Branch that ſprouteth from that roote, Fayth hath the preheminence inſinuated in this Preſcience and foreknowledge of God in theſe words: <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> The other is more open in the wordes following.</p>
               <q>Let all that call vpon the name of the Lord, depart from iniquitie.</q>
               <p>It is Fayth, that in a quicke apprehenſion ſwalloweth downe this Propoſition; <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> Knoweth, that is, Loueth thoſe that are his; and ſo inferreth this. Aſſumpt therevpon: and ſo loueth mee, that am one of his.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177637:19"/>
               <p>This Attribute of Knowledge, aſcribed to God, is of two ſortes. 1. <hi>Abſoluta,</hi> Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; ſo ſtiled of the Schoole-men, inaſmuch as all thinges ſimply, and abſolutely from all eternitie are knowne vnto God. Of this the ſpirit ſpeaketh thus:
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Neither is there any creature which is not manifeſt in his ſight: But all thinges are naked and open vnto his eyes.</hi> And to this appertaineth this ſentence of Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.11.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord knoweth the thoughtes of men, that they are but vaine.</hi> 2. The other is, <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialis,</hi> of more ſpeciall propertie, as by which he not onely knoweth the Elect, as he doth all other things; but alſo knoweth them for his owne, deuideth them from others: alloweth, and loueth them aboue all others: For this word, <hi>Knoweth,</hi> when it is giuen to God ſpeaking of the creature, very often in Scripture-language beareth ſuch a meaning; as where <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, <hi>The Lord knoweth the way of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>but the way of the vngodly ſhall periſh.</hi> As where Chriſt ſayth to the prating pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.
<note place="margin">Math. 7.23.</note> 
                  <hi>I know you not depart from mee, yee workers of iniquitie.</hi> As where <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>God hath not caſt away his people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.2.</note> 
                  <hi>which hee knew before.</hi> So doth <hi>Thomas</hi> take this word in his Scholie vpon the 8. Chapter to the <hi>Romans, Quos praeſciuit ſcientia appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationis, hos et praedeſtinauit:</hi> Thoſe whom
<pb facs="tcp:177637:19"/>he foreknew, in his knowledge of appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation; them alſo he predeſtinated. And the ſame Schoole man, is in the minde, that Gods effectuall will of conferring grace, is included in this his knowledge of approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thus <hi>Hugo de Sancto victore,</hi> in his notes vpon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes:</hi> And <hi>Ioachim,</hi> vpon the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> doe vnderſtand this worde. <hi>Augustine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. do perſeuer. Sanct. lib. 2. c. 18.</note> ſometimes doth not doubt, to take the Knowledge of God, for Gods Predeſtination, and to confounde them togeather; grounding his Iudgement vpon the Apoſtles aſſertion: <hi>God hath not caſt away his People, which he knew before.</hi> And ſuch are by his reckning, <hi>Filij in praeſcientia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rept. et gra. c. 9.</note> Sonnes in Gods foreknowledge, <hi>Qui in memoriali patris ſui inconcuſſa ſtabilitate conſcripti ſunt;</hi> Who are written downe in Gods rowles of remembrances, not to be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out. So <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſingeth vs the ſame ſonge,
<note place="margin">Cyrill expoſ. in Ioh. 7. c. 6.</note> where he ſayth: <hi>Chriſt knoweth his Sheepe, electing and foreſeeing them vnto eternall life, (as the Apostle telleth vs:) God hath not caſt away his people, which hee knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: for as the Lord, ſuch as he reprobateth, is ſayd not to know; as where he ſayth to the fooliſh Maydes, that had not Oyle for their Lightes, I know you not: ſo ſuch as hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinateth, and preordinateth vnto life, hee
<pb facs="tcp:177637:20"/>is rightly ſayd to know them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this is the true Fayth which ought to be in vs, to be throughly perſwaded, that wee are in the rancke and claſsie of Gods children, adopted in Chriſt Ieſu, and ſo to be in the fatherly fauour of God; and that ſo our ſaluation is ſealed vp in a Bagge.</p>
               <p>Without this Fayth, we cannot be graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Chriſt. But this Fayth ſufficeth vs, though not perfect, ſo it be true, though but ſmall as a Graine of Muſterd-ſeed, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der like a new borne Babe. In the Babe there can not be the action of Fayth, which is the knowledge of Chriſt, and confidence in him; yet is the Spirit and virtue thereof in it, which in time will ſhew it ſelfe. And this the Scriptures would haue vs beleeue,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> in all ſuch places as ſhew vs, that wee are ſaued by Fayth; and that without Fayth, it is impoſsible that we ſhould pleaſe God; yet withall, the perfecter our Fayth is, the greater is the power of it: and therefore we muſt endeauour all we may, to encreaſe our Fayth. And albeit wee receiue in this life, not the Tithe; but the firſt Fruites of Gods Spirit,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.23. 2. Cor. 1.22.</note> and but the earneſt thereof: (the firſt Fruites being but a Sheafe, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the whole Cornelande: and the Earneſt being as it were but a Pennie, for the payment of Poundes,) yet this Sheafe, this Pennie, ſerueth the turne to incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb facs="tcp:177637:20"/>vs into Chriſt. As the eye of an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> ſeruing him but to looke vp to the Braſen Serpent, auayled to cure the ſting of the fierie Serpent;
<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> ſo the pur-blind eye of our Fayth, if it can but turne vp the Ball to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Chriſt lifted vp vnto the Croſſe, it will be enough to cure the deadly wound, the old Serpent hath giuen vs. The Palſie ſhaking hand of a poore <hi>Lazar,</hi> may ſerue to receiue the deuotion of a Paſſenger, as well as the beſt, though the other can hold it faſteſt. Though the Bonie partes in mans body be the ſtrongeſt; yet there is as much life in the weake Fleſh, as in them. The weakeſt Ioynt of the body (ſo it be liuing) is as liuing as the reſt. So this is the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of Diuine prouidence in the body of the Church, that euery one of the Elect, the members thereof, ſhould haue ſo much Fayth meaſured out vnto them, as might ſuffice to their ſaluation. As hee that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered much Manna had not the more: and as hee that gathered leſſe, had not leſſe, but had enough as well as the other; ſo it is with Fayth, the food of the Soule: hee that hath the leaſt, hath enough to ſaue his Soule in the day of the Lord, as well as hee that hath the greateſt meaſure thereof.</p>
               <p>Thus Fayth is the Seale of our Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation vnto life, in aſmuch as none are cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereof, but the ſealed ſort: wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:177637:21"/>it is ſtiled,
<note place="margin">Tit 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>The Fayth of the elect.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> who had been <hi>Paules</hi> auditors,
<note place="margin">Act. 13.48.</note> ſayth: <hi>As many as were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned vnto life, beleeued.</hi> In this reſpect, <hi>Paul</hi> entituleth Fayth,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The earneſt of our adoption and inheritaunce.</hi> Men ſimply naturall, <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not the thinges that are of God;</hi> and ſo can not ſpanne or comprehend the Fayth. To this,
<note place="margin">Cum alibi, rum in libro de bono perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> giue all the Fathers conſent, that Fayth is the effect of Predeſtination. So <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> auoweth againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi> in ſundrie places.</p>
               <p>Now whereas others are ſayd to beleeue as the Deuils, <hi>They beleeue and tremble:</hi> as the temporizers of theſe dayes; it is ſo abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely and improperly ſayd of them. It is as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth: <hi>Alij cogitant, pij credunt,</hi> The Godly beleeue; others doe but thinke: The Fayth is not in them, but a kinde of Fancie onely.</p>
               <p>This Fayth is a harder matter then the Schoole of <hi>Rome</hi> conceiueth, who recke no more of it, then of an ordinarie gift of God; of <hi>a certaine light of the minde, by which one aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth to the word of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caniſ. op. ca. pa. Rhem. teſt in. 2. Cor. 15.5.</note> (as <hi>Caniſius</hi> hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitated: <hi>then of an actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of</hi> the <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> as the <hi>Rhemiſtes</hi> would haue it: to be onely occupied in generalities, and neuer to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende to application in particular,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.5. Luk. 8.13. Iam. 2.19.</note> as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dradius</hi> dreameth. For ſuch a Fayth, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Reprobates may be owners of: for their
<pb facs="tcp:177637:21"/>mindes may be illuminated in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the trueth; and they may bee throughly perſwaded of it. And therefore they haue this action of vnderſtanding. And this is the generall Fayth that taketh vp thinges in groſſe; which the Deuilles themſelues haue.</p>
               <p>Wee teach and prooue, that Fayth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in a facultie of apprehending and applying Chriſt: that to <hi>Beleeue, Apprehend,</hi> and to <hi>Receiue</hi> Chriſt, are all one. Thus Saint <hi>John</hi> compoundeth and confoundeth them,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.12.</note> where he ſayth; <hi>As many as receiued him, to them he gaue power to be the Sounes of God, euen to them that beleeue in his Name.</hi> Thus is Faith an application of Chriſt in ſpeciall to it ſelfe: as a poore man when an almes is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him, he doth put foorth his hand and draw it in againe vnto himſelfe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the almes his owne.
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.27.</note> This is the reaſon of the Metaphor of <hi>Putting on of Chriſt,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp by the Apoſtle, where hee entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the nature of Fayth. But Chriſt is onely Put on by way of application in particular, of his righteouſneſſe laide to our heartes, as the Garment is applyed vnto the backe, when it is put vpon it. Hitherto hath reference the manducation and pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, which is by Fayth.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35.</note> Now the meate and drinke that wee take downe to doe vs good, muſt be taſted, minced by the
<pb facs="tcp:177637:22"/>Teeth, conueyed into the Stomacke, dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and after all theſe, be particularly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to their ſeuerall partes that are to be nouriſhed by them.</p>
               <p>Hence it is that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prayeth for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>That Christ may dwell in their heartes by fayth:</hi> Which can not be without the apprehenſion of him. He therefore may properly be ſayd to beleeue, that can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and truely ſay of himſelfe, that he is throughly perſwaded in his conſcience, that he is reconciled vnto God for all his ſinnes, and is accepted vnto eternall life in him. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth both by practiſe and precept: as where hauing firſt ſet downe the generall Propoſition:
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>A man is not iuſtified by the workes of the Law; but by Faith in Christ Ieſu:</hi> Hee immediatly inferreth the Application of it to himfelfe in particular: <hi>Wee haue beleeued in Ieſu Chriſt, that wee might be iustified by the Fayth of Chriſt.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath in the 20. verſe more ſpecially he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vſe thereof, thus vnto himſelfe: <hi>I liue by faith in the Sonne of God, who hath loued mee, and giuen himſelfe for mee.</hi> Ney ther doth <hi>Paule</hi> take this as his prerogatiue, or peculiar, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue others; but only ſetteth out himſelfe for an example vnto vs, that wee ſhould ſo inſtruct and comfort our ſelues: Wherefore elſe where he ſayeth,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>For this cauſe, was J re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vnto mercie, that Ieſus Christ ſhould first
<pb facs="tcp:177637:22"/>ſhew on mee, all long ſuffring, vnto the enſample of them, which ſhall in time to come beleeue in him, vnto eternall life.</hi> And how this is incident to all beleeuers, in an other place he telleth vs, where hauing thus ſaid, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning himſelfe. <hi>I Iudge all thinges but doung,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>that I might win Chriſt, and might be found in him, not hauing mine owne righteousneſse, which is of the Lawe, but that which is through the faith of Christ, euen the righteousnes which is of God through faith:</hi> He teacheth vs, that this is direction for vs,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> and the inherent condition of Fayth; <hi>Let as many as be perfect, be thus minded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Fayth liueih not in ſuſpenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Hope and Feare, as the Crow that flyeth betweene Heauen and Earth; but neſtleth herſelfe in the Woundes of Chriſt, as Doues in the cliftes and holes of Rockes. By this, <hi>Wee ſtand,</hi> ſayth Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> nay,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> by this, <hi>Wee liue,</hi> ſayth the Prophet <hi>Abacuc.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Abac. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Fayth</hi> is the Spirit and Soule of the New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Wee haue the name that we liue: but indeed we are dead towardes God, if wee beleeue not; <hi>If Peraduenture,</hi> are not wordes that proceed from the mouth of Fayth, but it is the pronuntiation of <hi>Babylon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierom. 51.8.</note> as it is thus written: <hi>Bring Balme for her Sore, Jf ſhe may he healed. Peraduenture,</hi> is a Plaiſter to be ſet on the Sore and ſide of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177637:23"/>whom <hi>Simon Peter</hi> ſummoning to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<note place="margin">Act. 8.22.</note> ſaith: <hi>Pray to God, that if it be poſsible, the thoughtes of thine heart may be forgiuen thee.</hi> Wherefore make wee not our caſe, like the caſe of the Elephant, who lyeth downe, and cannot riſe againe: Let vs not ſo farre bend the Bowe, as to breake it: But in the cauſe of Faith, let vs take vp <hi>Peters</hi> Text: <hi>Maiſter, it is good for vs to be heere.</hi> Let vs taſte of the Tree of Life, and our eyes ſhall bee opened. Let vs ſprinckle our heartes, with the blood of the Lambe, and the deſtructiue Angell ſhall not hurt vs: Let vs ſay with the Spouſe,
<note place="margin">Cantic. 3.4.</note> in the <hi>Canticles: J haue found him, whom my Soule loueth, I will hold him faſt, and will not let him goe.</hi> The forgiuenes of our finns, is an Article of our Chriſtian faith; ſo that hee that beleeueth it not, is not a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>This Faith is required of vs, through our whole life, but cheifely, about the time of our death; (when our Wealth, and Wel wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, our Senſes and Senſualities, and all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſollaces, and ſuccours forſake vs.) For then Faith enforceth vs, to goe out of our ſelues, and to runne to the mercie of God, as to our Cittie of refuge; Then is Faith the hande of the Soule, by which wee draw in Chriſt to our ſelues, with all his Benefites. Then is Faith the mouth of the heart, by which wee feede on Chriſt, as on a reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,
<pb facs="tcp:177637:23"/>eating his Body, and drinking his Blood, vnto eternall life. Then is Faith the Foote of the minde, which enableth vs to walke with God, the meanes whereby wee are familiar with him. Then is Faith the Eare, by which wee heare God ſpeaking to vs, out of the word. Then is Faith, the Tongue of the Soule, by which wee talke with God, and inuocate his moſt holy and reuerende name. Wherefore <hi>Luther</hi> was wont to ſay, That men become beſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, when they are at Deaths doore. When <hi>Dauid</hi> ſawe nothing but preſent death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 30.6.</note> the People determining with themſelues to ſtone him; his <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> that he immediately tooke out, was in the Lord his God. And the vſe that he made to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, of the Promiſes of God, was the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Ioye,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.49.50.</note> and the lifter vp of his head, in the time of trouble; where he ſayth: <hi>Remember the promife made to thy Seruant, wherein thou hast cauſed mee to put my truſt: It is my comfort in my trouble, for thy promiſe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee.</hi> As elſe where, where he ſayeth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.25.</note> 
                  <hi>My Fleſh, and my heart faileth: But God is the ſtrength of my heart, &amp; my portion for euer.</hi> The <hi>Jſraelites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.14.</note> when they had beene ſtroken by firie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents in the Wilderneſſe, and their wounds were deadly; they caſt vp their eyes to the Brazen Serpent, (as God would haue them,) and they were forthwith healed. So when
<pb facs="tcp:177637:24"/>the fiery Dart of death, ſtriketh vs at the very heart, fixe wee the eyes of our fayth vpon Chriſt, lifted vp vpon the Croſſe, and ſo by the Path-way, and Region of death, wee ſhall haue the through paſſage, and entry, vnto eternall life.</p>
               <p>All this while I deny not, but that this fayth in the beſt of the bunch, skirmiſheth with doubtes. Hee that neuer doubted of his election, neuer yet beleeued it. As he that is in health, feeleth many grudginges, and motions vnto ſickneſſe; which he ſhould neuer feele, were hee not ſound. So the true beleeuer feeleth many quaimes, which he ſhould not haue had, had he not beleeued: For in Man, there is a double eſtate, as he is compounded of Nature, and Grace. By the firſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.5.</note> (that is Nature,) hee and his fleſh; (as Man and Wife,) maketh but one Boody, wherfore the one conſenteth, and is acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the other. When the fleſh ſinneth, man alſo ſinneth, that conſiſteth of Fleſh: yea when the Fleſh periſheth, the Man peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth; as a louing couple, they liue and die togeather. By the ſecond, albeit his Fleſh be about him,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.17. Rom. 8.1.</note> yet hee and his Fleſh haue made a diuorce.</p>
               <p>This Diuorce is made, when a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to diſpleaſe himſelfe, and to hate the Fleſh, and the filthy fruites thereof. Now vpon this Diuorce, they are no more
<pb facs="tcp:177637:24"/>one, but twaine; and are ſo deuided, as the one hath nothing to doe with the other. In this caſe, although the Eleſh bringeth foorth ſinne, and periſheth: yet the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is not in the ſtate of damnation. Therefore howſoeuer the Fleſh fathereth doubtes, recount with thy ſelfe this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce, and that thou art now wedded vnto Chriſt; and ſo diſclaime thy ſinnes, as none of thine, baſely begotten, and baſtardly brattes. Say I doubt; but I deteſt my doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, I am no cauſe of them: But my Fleſh is the occaſion, which ſhall periſh, when as my Soule ſhalbe ſaued by Ieſus Chriſt. In the meane while, cure this Diſeaſe of thy doubtinges, with theſe preſeruatiues, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe thee.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That it is Gods poſitiue, and expreſſe precept, thou ſhouldeſt beleeue in Chriſt:
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3 23.</note> His Precept runneth thus. <hi>This is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, that wee beleeue in the Name of his ſonne Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Thou dareſt not breake the eight Commaundement of the morall Law; <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi> And why art thou ſo bould as to breake this, this being as forcible a binder as the other?</p>
               <p n="2">2 That God his promiſes of ſaluation in Chriſt, are indefinite, and generall, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding none. Let one of them, heere ſtand in the roome of manie. <hi>So God loued the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>that he gaue his only begotten Sonne; that
<pb facs="tcp:177637:25"/>whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</hi> When the Prince ſealeth his generall pardon for all Felons; euery man taketh the benefite of it, though he bee not ſet downe by his name in it: But God hath gone further with thee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo; he hath particularly ſigned thee thy Pardon. 1. Firſt, in the Seale of Baptiſme. 2. Secondly, by that of the Supper of the Lord, wherfore ſtand faſt in the faith which thou haſt made, and doubt no farther of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That Diſtruſt and Deſpaire,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.18.</note> diſpleaſeth God almoſt as much as any other ſinne; for thereby thou art no longer the Childe of <hi>Abraham, To hope againſt hope,</hi> as thou oughteſt. Thou robbeſt God of his Glory, in aſmuch as thou makeſt his infinite Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, an vnderling to thy ſinnes. Thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt God a lyer, who hath plighted this promiſe to thee of forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: Nay, thou doeſt iuſtifie Sathan before God; for God hath ſayd it, ſworne it, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it with the redde precious blood of Chriſt: and yet wee rather beleeue the ſuggeſtion of Sathan, that the Iuſtice of God is not to be appeaſed. This Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire is a maladie immedicable: for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee doe as the wilfull diſeaſed man, who when as the Chyrurgian would heale his ſoare, hee thruſteth his Nayles againe into it, and ſetteth it backward.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177637:25"/>
               <p>But all this while, how ſhould a man know that hee is thus Sealed, and hath this indeleble character of Fayth ſtamped on his Soule? For many a mans Fayth is but fayned, and formed to the times. And ſuch do but beguile themſelues, while they ſtand in opinion they doe beleeue, and beleeue not at all.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, that ſuch reſemble them, that dreame that they are Princes and great States, and awake ſtarke Beggars. Such as truly beleeue, doe know they beleeue, euen as hee that hath a Iewell in his hand, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he hath it. For if a man that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth an other man on his word, doth know that he beleeueth him: how much more ſhall hee, whoſe heart is inſpired with true Fayth, by the worke of the holy Ghoſt, to beleeue the Goſpell, know that hee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it? If a man might not know whether hee hath this true Fayth or noe; how is it that the Apoſtle perſwadeth vs thus: <hi>Prooue your ſelues whether yee be in the Fayth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5.</note> thereby inſinuating, that it is to be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, prooued, and knowne, whether we do beleeue? So that as hee that vnderſtandeth, knoweth that he vnderſtandeth: So he that beleeueth, knoweth that hee beleeueth. Wherfore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> thus ſpeaketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: <hi>I know whom I haue beleeued.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.12.</note> A poynt which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> thus concludeth,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.24.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177637:26"/>ſaying:
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Hereby wee know, that he abideth in vs: euen by that ſpirit, which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs. Auguſtine</hi> is plentifull in this cauſe: I will charge you,
<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de Trinit. 13. c. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vidit fidem eſſe in corde ſuo ſi credat: ſi non videt cam deeſſe.</hi> Euery one perceiueth that hee hath fayth in his heart, if he beleeueth: If not, he findeth that he is without it.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. 112.</note> Againe, where he ſayeth: <hi>Credens videt propriam ſuam fidem, per quam reſpondet ſe credere ſine dubitatione.</hi> The beleeuer feeleth his owne Faith, by which he beleeueth without doubtinges.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. de Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. c. 8.</note> In an other place, thus: <hi>Qui diligit Fratrem ſuum, magisſcit dilec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem per quam diligit, quam Fratrem quem diligit.</hi> Hee that looueth his Brother, knoweth the loue, wherewith he loueth him; better then he knoweth his Brother whom hee loueth. This, and ſuch like ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Gods Predeſtination, are not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply effects, but ſuch effects thereof, as they alſo may be ſaide to be Seales of it. For God to vsward, is like to the Sunne. The Sunne when it ſhineth on vs (and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, looketh vs on the face,) printeth in ſuch ſort, the Image of his light in our eyes; as wee alſo are made partakers of the ſame light, and are enabled to looke vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:177637:26"/>Sunne, &amp; the light thereof. For the beames of the Sunne, ſtriking vpon vs, haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percuſsion and reflexe towards the Sunne: So the Lord, the Sonne of Righteouſneſſe, looketh vpon vs, and knoweth vs to be his: And then the Elect being made partakers of his Light and Knowledge; hee maketh vs likewiſe to know him. Heereto ſerue theſe words of our Sauiour: <hi>J know my ſheepe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 10.14.</note> Inferring therevpon in the next place, <hi>And J am knowne of mine:</hi> So the firſt, is the cauſe of the latter; and the latter, alwayes follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the former: as if he ſhould haue ſayd. While I acknowledge them for mine, I make them to haue my light &amp; knowledge, to acknowledge mee their Shephearde. Both theſe, are put togeather by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 49.</note> where hee ſayth; <hi>Seeing yee know God, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are knowne of God.</hi> Where hee teacheth, that therefore becauſe God knew the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> who firſt acknowledged them, for his: hee conſequently imparted this his owne Wiſedome to them, and brought them to that paſſe, to acknowledge the true God to be their God.</p>
               <p>The like may be ſayd of the Loue of God, wherewith he loued vs in Chriſt to eternall life, before the groundworke of the World was laide. God in louing vs, hath left an impreſsion and obſignation of his loue in our heartes, by which wee returne,
<pb facs="tcp:177637:27"/>and retorte this loue, and loue him againe; and as it were by the reflexion of theſe Sun-beames, ſtriking into our heartes, are prouoked to loue him. For Gods loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, beeing by nature eternall, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth at his full appoynted time, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine loue in vs, ſeruing to the eternitie of his glorie.
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.19.</note> Hence it is that Saint <hi>John</hi> ſayth: <hi>Not that we loued him, but that he firſt loued vs.</hi> As if hee ſhould thus ſay; By ſetting the Seale of his Loue vpon our heartes, hee ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth thus much, that wee in the rereward ſhould loue him as a Father: Wherefore by the ſoliditie of that loue, by which wee haue a feeling that wee loue God, wee are made to know how large the dimenſions of that loue of God are, by which from all eternitie in Chriſt, hee hath embraced vs. Now what is this loue elſe, but Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? So our Election, by which we are put apart in Chriſt from the reſidue of the World, ſetteth a kind of Image of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon vs: that is, it begetteth an other Election, by which wee renounce all other Gods, and know no other elſe but the true God, to be adored and worſhipped; and not onely as wee gather the cauſe from the effect, but as wee draw a Picture from the preſident; and as from the forme of the Seale in the Waxe, we eaſily conceiue what is the Image of the Seale it ſelfe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177637:27"/>
               <p>And thus much of this firſt Seale, which reſpecteth God, in theſe wordes; <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other Seale followeth, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth our ſelues, in the ſequell, thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Let euery one that calleth vpon the Name of the Lord, depart from iniquitie.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>To Fayth, the proper indument of the Elect, a ſpeciall Seale of Election, Good workes an other Seale thereof, is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly adioyned. Good workes can neuer be ſundred from Fayth, as Scriptures and Fathers teach, and our Church beleeue. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of ſuch, who making great wordes of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> but denie him in their workes, ſayth; <hi>They prefeſse they know God; but by workes they denie him, and are abominable, and diſobedient; and to euery good worke reprobate:</hi> Where, to denie God, is to denie the Fayth. In an other place hee ſayth,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>if there be any that prouideth not for his owne, and namely for them of his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he hath denied the Fayth:</hi> Now hee that denieth the Fayth, can not haue Fayth. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth; <hi>Hee that ſayth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>I know him, and keepeth not his commaundementes, is a lyar:</hi> Where hee concludeth that to be a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and a falſe Fayth, which hath not ioynt commerce with the performaunce of his preceptes: but a counterfait Fayth, is no Fayth at all: Therefore they goe both hand
<pb facs="tcp:177637:28"/>in hand togither; Fayth &amp; Good workes, and will not part company.
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> Fayth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Good workes, is dead: It is Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his theoreme, and caſe diuinitie. But dead Fayth, is no more Fayth, then a dead Man, is a Man: The Fathers with one conſent, teach the ſame.
<note place="margin">Orig. in Ezech. Hom. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Origen</hi> ſayeth: <hi>Male credit quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> peccat.</hi> Hee that is a ſinner, is but a ſimple beleeuer.
<note place="margin">In epiſt. ad Rom. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 10.</note> In his Scholie vpon the <hi>Romans,</hi> hee prooueth the ſame thus: <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis qui credit in eum non erubeſcit: erubeſcit autem omnis qui peccat: ergo qui adhuc ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccati incurrit, credere non videtur.</hi> Euery one that beleeueth in him, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed: but euery one that ſinneth, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed: therefore, hee that falleth into the ſhame of ſinne, ſeemeth as yet not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.
<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſingeth the ſame ſong, where he ſaith: <hi>Quomodo dixit ſe credere in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, qui non facit quod Chriſtus facere praecepit?</hi> How doth hee ſay that hee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in Chriſt, who doth not that which Chriſt hath commaunded him? <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is as peremptorie in the Point,
<note place="margin">Amb. lib. 6. Epiſt. 36.</note> where he ſaith; <hi>Vbi quis caeperit luxuriart, incipit deuiare a vera fide;</hi> Hee that ſwaggereth, ſwarueth from the Fayth.
<note place="margin">Aug. in Ioh. ſerm. 61.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hereunto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth teſtimonie in ſundry places; as where hee ſayth, <hi>Qui fidem habet ſine ſpe
<pb facs="tcp:177637:28"/>et dilectione, Chriſtum eſſe credit, non in Chriſtum credit;</hi> Whoſoeuer hath Fayth, without Hope and Loue, beleueth that Chriſt is; but hee beleeueth not in Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Aug. de fide et operib. c. 23.</note> Againe where he ſayth: <hi>Inſoperabilis eſt bona vita a fide quae per dilectionem opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: immo ueró ipſa eſt bona vita:</hi> Good life is not to be ſeuered from Fayth which worketh by Loue: yea Fayth is of it ſelfe, good life. Wherefore the 12. Article of the Chriſtian confeſsion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is moſt ſound, which profeſſeth in this wiſe; <hi>Good workes are the fruites of Iuſtifying fayth, and doe neceſſarily ſpring and grow from thence:</hi> Wherefore Fayth beeing the badge of the Elect; and Workes inſeparably being the effectes thereof: the ſequell muſt needes bee, that Good workes muſt be alſo the Liuerie of the Elect, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be knowne. Which ſtoppeth the mouth of our carnall Epicures; who vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the foundation of Gods immutable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of our election, would lay the ſtructure and compoſition of a diſſolute conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while they reaſon thus: <hi>Wee may liue as wee list; becauſe if wee be predeſtinated vnto life, wee can not be loſt.</hi> But ſuch are to know, that the <hi>End,</hi> and the <hi>Meanes,</hi> that make to the end, muſt needes goe togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:177637:29"/>Fayth and Good Workes inſeparably accompanie the worke of our Election. God glorifieth not the Elect, before hee hath Called and Iuſtified them: yea, before they Beleeue, and declare by their Workes that they doe beleeue.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.10.</note> Hence is it that the Apoſtle ſayth; <hi>Wee are created in Chriſt Ieſu vnto good Workes, which God hath ordained, that wee ſhould walke in them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> And hereto ſerue theſe inferences of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> of Loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.19.</note> vnto whic h we are choſen: and of a good Conſcience, which as an impartible companion, is of the Fayth of the Elect. This endeauour to performe Good works, is to all the Elect neceſſarie,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note> as <hi>Peter</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, where he willeth vs, that wee <hi>make ſure our Election,</hi> and <hi>Vocation, by good workes;</hi> as many Copies haue it; not to God, our vocation being certaine vnto him before the Worldes creation: but to our ſelues, &amp; to our neighboures. This is one of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt vſes we make of Good workes; that by them not as cauſes, but effectes of our Election and Fayth, wee our ſelues and our brethren, are aſſured and ſecured of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Where the mouthes of the <hi>Pelagians</hi> are ſtopped, who make the foreſight of our Fayth, and Workes in God, the cauſe of our Saluation: when as of the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary-ſide, God hath predeſtinated vs to Fayth, and Good workes; becauſe he hath
<pb facs="tcp:177637:29"/>choſen vs to eternall life.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.25.</note> Wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh cautelouſly, where he ſayth; <hi>Job<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy of the Lord to be faythfull:</hi> he ſaith not, Becauſe I was to be faithfull. As where he ſpeaketh in the ſame manner, thus; <hi>That we ſhould be vnblamable,</hi> not becauſe we were to bee ſuch. As againe where hee ſayth;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee are created in Chriſt Ieſu vinto Good workes, which God hath ordained, that wee ſhould walke in them;</hi> not becauſe wee did them. As finally, where he ſaith;
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>The Grace of God hath appeared, that wee ſhould liue ſoberly, righteouſly, godly:</hi> not becauſe wee were ſo to doe. It can not be rightly ſaid, that God firſt foreſeeth that men are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and afterward predeſtinateth them to beleeue: Becauſe whom hee foreknew ſhould beleeue, therefore hee foreknew it,
<note place="margin">Contra. Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.</note> becauſe hee decreed it. Wherefore <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> calleth them, <hi>The Elect, who are fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, that they ſhould beleeue:</hi> wherefore ſuch as by Gods grace are delighted in Good workes; in them there is a certaine ſigne and ſeale, that they beleeue in Chriſt, and ſo that they are elected in Chriſt vnto eternall life.</p>
               <p>Fayth is of the nature of a Tree in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which naturally of it ſelfe, bringeth foorth fruites; ſo that there is no need that the Tree be commaunded to yeeld her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe:
<pb facs="tcp:177637:30"/>So the faythfull man without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action diſpoſeth himſelfe to be fruitfull in Good workes, the Law of God being graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his heart, ſo that his delight is dayly in the ſame: So that of his owne accord, he doth Good workes, as of him ſelfe hee ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, hee drinketh, ſeeth, heareth, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth ſuch faculties as are incident to Nature: As hee that is thirſtie doth but ſtay vntill drinke come: and as hee that is hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, expecteth his meate, and then wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and naturally hee taketh them both: So the Faythfull man, hungrie and thirſtie of Righteouſneſſe, taketh the aduantage of all occaſions, to doe the Workes thereof. Although Fayth alone iuſtifieth and knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Marriage knotte betweene the Soule &amp; Chriſt; and is properly the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment, and the ſigne <hi>Tau</hi> which muſt Protect vs from the power of the euill Angels; yet Fayth is neuer ſeuered from Charitie: Wherefore the Faythfull are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to Orchardes, Vines, and Trees, that bring foorth Fruite in ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>The Church by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is reſembled to a Vine,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 5.7.</note> furniſhed with a Wine-preſſe and Towre for the purpoſe: wherefore Chriſt ſayth;
<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.1.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the Vine, and my Father is the Huſbandman; euery Branch that beareth not fruite in mee, hee taketh away: and euery
<pb facs="tcp:177637:30"/>one that beareth fruite, he purgeth it, that it may bring foorth more fruite.</hi> Wherefore, God is ſayd to haue come downe to the <hi>Garden of Nuttes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſee the fruites of the Valley, to ſee if the Vine budded, and the Pomegranats flouriſhed.</hi> Moreouer, we are to <hi>Bring foorth Fruites in patience:</hi> For God,
<note place="margin">Luk. 8.15.</note> the Lord of the Vineyard, commeth to his Vine with a pruning Knife in his hand, to toppe and cutte off the luxurious Branches, that we might bring foorth more Fruite, and be in better liking.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians are <hi>Trees of righteouſneſse,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 47.4.12</note> 
                  <hi>gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing by the Riuers of the Sanctuarie:</hi> But not ſuch Trees as ours are; for they take roote vpwarde in Heauen in Chriſt; and their branches grow downeward, and fructifie among men. Wherefore theoricall Religion is not enough. It ſerueth not our turnes to beare the name of Chriſtians, if wee liue not as Chriſtians. True Pietie, challengeth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iniquitie. <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſmooth Voyce, and <hi>Eſaus</hi> rough Garment, agree not togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Wee beare <hi>Adams</hi> diſeaſe about vs, rather taſting of the Tree of Knowledge; then of the Tree of Life: <hi>Scientia,</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; weigheth heauier in the Ballence, then <hi>Conſcientia,</hi> Conſcience; therefore our Sorrow muſt be added to that part, to adde more weight vnto it. Such Vocaliſtes, haue
<pb facs="tcp:177637:31"/>their Repulſe alreadie in the perſons of thoſe prating Profeſſors; whom Chriſt ſhooke off thus: <hi>J know you not, depart from mee yee workers of iniquitie:</hi> For Light and Darkneſſe will haue no entercourſe togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: God and <hi>Belial</hi> will not bargaine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.</note> Hee cannot abide a ſinfull body, of whom it is written: <hi>Righteouſneſse and Truth is the preparation of his ſeate.</hi> Hee that will fill a Glaſſe-bottle with Hony that ſtood full of Vineger before, muſt firſt emptie it of the Vineger before it can be capable of the Hony. The veſſels of our Soules are full vp to the brim with the ſharpe Vineger of our ſinnes; God would gladly fill them with the Hony-bleſsinges of his goodneſſe: Wherefore wee muſt firſt be purged and rinced of our former iniquities. <hi>Lethalia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata non ſunt Chriſtianorum, ſed Ethnieorum,</hi> Deadly ſinnes are not of Chriſtians, but of Heathens. Wherefore our Circumciſion went before our Reconciliation; to ſignifie that the circumciſion of our ſinnes, muſt goe before our pacification with God. Wee are not vnder the Law, but vnder Grace. What then? Therefore Iniquitie muſt not thus ſet vp a Monarchie in vs: it is <hi>Paules</hi> conſequent, and it is neceſſarily inferred. With our new Profeſsion, wee muſt caſt off our old Conuerſation; as the Eagle caſteth her Bill: And we muſt know that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:177637:31"/>of God is not in word, but in worke. <hi>Dauids</hi> monition in theſe words; <hi>Yee that loue God, ſee that yee hate the thing that is euill;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 97.</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth in effect, the wordes onely varied: to this preſent direction of the Apoſtle, in our text: <hi>Let euery one that calleth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of the Lord, depart from iniquitie. Aulus Fuluins,</hi> on a time, eſpying his Sonne in <hi>Catilines</hi> Campe among the rebellious route, would haue put him to the Sword, telling him, that hee begot him not for <hi>Catiline,</hi> but for his Countrie: So this is not the condition of our creation, or the conſideratio of our regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that we ſhould ſerue vnder ſinne, the profeſſed Enemie vnto God, but that wee ſhould ſerue him in righteouſneſſe, and true holyneſſe, all the dayes of our life. <hi>Demades</hi> in times paſt, ſeeing <hi>Philip</hi> the King, want only diſpoſed among his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, inſulting vpon the miſfortunes of his Priſoners, whom he had then in durance; thus grauely and aduiſedly cenſured his leuitie: Sithens Fortune and good lucke, hath impoſed vpon thee, the perſon of <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon,</hi> (that is of a valiant and victorious Prince,) mayeſt thou not be aſhamed to play the <hi>Therſites,</hi> (that is a Man of vnſeemely demeanour?) It is a huge diſgrace to a Kings Sonne any way, to conuerſe with raſcall Company: So, wee beeing adopted the Sonnes of God, by grace in Chriſt Ieſu, it
<pb facs="tcp:177637:32"/>will bee an indeleble turpitude in vs, to haue any dealing with ſinne &amp; iniquitie: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore remember wee our calling, and let euery one of vs that call vpon God, bidde adiewe to iniquitie.</p>
               <p>Wee will conclude all, with a ſhort ſuppu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation &amp; ſuruey of the multiplicitie of eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall vſe, that this Text tendereth vs.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt, heere is liuely demonſtrance of the vncreated wiſedome of God, who in his eternall counſaile, hath foreſeene, and in ſinguler wiſedome, hath diſpoſed of euery ones eſtate, and this foundation, of his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, ſtandeth ſure, without poſsibilitie of any alteration.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Heere is alſo conſideration of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer abſolute, that he is able, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all reſiſtaunce, to ſaue all ſuch, as are appointed thereunto by his diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, heere is Mercy, taking Iuſtice by the Heele, and ſupplanting it as <hi>Jacob</hi> did <hi>Eſau,</hi> in ſauing ſuch by his gratious election, through the hand of a Mediator, which were determined to deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Fourthly, heere is argument of liquide, Ioy and comfort, that this foundation of our ſaluation is the Lordes, it muſt needes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be vnreſiſtable and moſt ſure.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Fiftly, whereas God hath preordinated vs to life, and hath giuen vs the meanes in
<pb facs="tcp:177637:32"/>his word to attaine the certificat of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler election, let vs take the counſaile S. <hi>Peter</hi> giueth vs,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note> to endeuour to make our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſure vnto vs. In the world, men looke well to the aſſuraunce of ſuch Landes and Poſſeſsions as they purchaſe, that they may be ſure to them, and to their Heires; how much more ſtandeth it vs in hand, to make ſure to our Soules, the heauenly inheritance, purchaſed for vs at ſo deare a price as the blood of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Further, hence ariſeth Patience in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, in aſmuch as,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Thoſe whom hee knew before, hee alſo predeſtinated to be made like to the Image of his Sonne;</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſetteth it downe: now wherein our conformitie with his Sonne ſtandeth, hee elſe-where ſheweth vs, where he layeth it downe thus:
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>In the fellowſhip of his afflictions, &amp; by being made confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable vnto his death.</hi> Wherefore they feede vpon a fond Fancie, which is a ſtrong falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, who make an eſtimate of the Graces of God towardes them, by the meaſure and proportion of their worldly proſperitie; that the Lord heere affordeth them. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth them otherwiſe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.22.</note> where he ſayeth: <hi>God to ſhew his wrath, and to make his power knowne, ſuffereth with long patience, the veſsels of wrath prepared vnto destruction.</hi> The Sheepe that are highly kept in the better Paſtures, come ſooneſt to the ſlaughter,
<pb facs="tcp:177637:33"/>when as ſuch as feede on the Common, liue a longer time.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Moreouer, wee are heere armed, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to withſtand all offence, that wee might otherwiſe take vp in the ſenſe of the contempt, that is caſt vpon the Ghoſpell, and in the ſenſeleſſe ignoraunce of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, while wee ponder this in our mindes, that nothing contingently, or caſually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, but according to the purpoſe and foreknowledge of God, the Lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing who are his. In this reſpect, Gods Miniſters are not to diſcourage them ſelues, and to be out of heart, in that their labours haue no better ſucceſſe in the heartes of their hearers, &amp; bring foorth ſuch ſlender fruites, while they fixe their thoughtes vpon the Decree of God, of ſauing ſome, and of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting other ſome; it belonging alſo to the ſayd Decree, that ſome are called ſooner, and ſome later.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Moreouer, whereas the Lord knoweth who are his; and ſome there be, whom hee is ſayd not to know: wee are thereby ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with no ſmall feare. It is the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and application the Apoſtle maketh from the exciſion and extirpation of the <hi>Jewes</hi> (the naturall Branches) and the inſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Through vnbeliefe they are broken off; and thou ſtandeſt by Fayth: be not high minded, but feare.</hi> There is nothing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb facs="tcp:177637:33"/>to them, but may befall vs: for others examples, are our Looking-glaſſes. <hi>Judas</hi> was tearmed an Incarnate Deuill; and his end was moſt fearefull: but without the greater ſupportation of Gods grace, wee ſhould not onely betray Chriſt with <hi>Judas;</hi> but worſer then the <hi>Jewes,</hi> wee ſhould a thouſand wayes crucifie him. Conſider we with our ſelues, whether there be not now in Hell, ſuch who were of better conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then wee, while wee liued heere on earth. <hi>Iſai</hi> calleth the people of his time,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>The people of Sodom,</hi> and, <hi>the people of Gomorah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 Finally, from the clauſe and concluſion of this ſentence, <hi>Let euery one, who calleth on the Name of the Lord, depart from Iniquitie:</hi> direction vnto Sanctification aryſeth; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, whom God hath choſen vnto life, hee hath alſo choſen vnto newneſſe of life.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee hath choſen vs</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>before the foundation of the world, that wee ſhould be holy, and without blame before him in loue:</hi> Whereto anſwereth, that which hee hath elſe-where in the ſame Letter;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee are created in Chriſt Jeſus, vnto good workes, which God hath ordained that wee ſhould walke in them.</hi> Wee haue the ſame Diuinitie deliuered vs in his writing to the <hi>Theſsalonians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning choſen you to ſaluation, through ſanctification of the Spirit, and the Fayth of trueth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> The Elect are ſtiled, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſels of honour:</hi> Wherefore ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:177637:34"/>as will be of that nature,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.21.</note> for that high ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and not be Disſhes of diſgrace, muſt ſo carrie themſelues, as they may be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among ſuch. But while wee ſoake our ſelues in our Sinnes, and lie wallowing in our Wickedneſſe, we are worſe then Treen Trayes, &amp; Veſſels of the vildeſt vſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer. It is ſo ſet downe, and eſtabliſhed by order, that the Sunne ſhould giue vs his light by day, and the Moone by night, and this ſtanding wherein they were primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely placed, they ſtill keepe. Yea euery Creature in her kinde, keepeth the courſe, at the firſt prefixed them, in the creation of all things. The Graſſe groweth, Trees fruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, according to the bleſsing pronounced by the mouth of God vpon them, when they were firſt in beeing, the verie ende and purpoſe of their beeing; thus are all Chriſtians, Trees that are planted by the right hand of God, to giue their fruite in due ſeaſon, this beeing the period and ende of their election, their holy conuerſation. If thou ſhouldſt paſſe by a ground, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou ſhouldſt ſee a beautifull Vine, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently kept, encloſed with a wall, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could hurt it, thou wouldeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the owner thereof was a carefull man, a good Husband indeed: ſo is euery one of vs to keepe our bodyes and ſoules in that godly and holy manner, as the verie
<pb facs="tcp:177637:34"/>aduerſarie to our Religion, be hee an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, beholding vs, may haue occaſion to reuerence our Religion, and to ſay, Great is the God of the Chriſtians. In the ſetting vp of an Houſe, firſt we lay the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then the Sides and Walles round about, and then the Roofe the vppermoſt part thereof. Fayth is the Foundation of this our Houſe: Good workes are the Walles and the reſt of the Building that is to be ioyned to this Foundation.</p>
               <p>To the pulling downe of an Houſe, the courſe is quite contrarie to that which was taken when it was firſt erected; for that which was ſet vp laſt was the Roofe; and with the Roofe, we beginne to reaue it and we come to the Foundation at the laſt. So the Deuill, ſeeking the ruine of vs all, hee firſt aſſaulteth our Good workes, the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt of our Building; our Almes, our Faſtes, our Prayers, our Charitie: and then he layeth at the Foundation of our Fayth, and ſayth; Downe with it, downe with it, euen to the ground.</p>
               <p>Finally, this parcell of Scripture, is the very Period of all the Scripture, as the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of all the Workes of God, done, and yet in doing, towardes vs. They haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny endes and purpoſes beſide; the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall whereof, is the Glorie of God: the reſt come in at the ſecond hand, and are
<pb facs="tcp:177637:35"/>ſeruantes vnto this, as ordinated and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred to this ſeruice and office of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and ſetting ſoorth the excellencie of this Glorie.</p>
               <p>Now among thoſe of the ſecondarie ſort, this eaſily is the chiefe, <hi>A zeale to Pietie: a diligent endeauour to depart from Iniquitie.</hi> The whole Scripture is reſolued into Law, and Goſpell. Hiſtorie is a midling betweene both, and an appurtenaunce vnto them. The whole Law is abridged and ſummed in this ſentence, <hi>Declina a malo; et fac bonum:</hi> Eſchew that is euill; and enſue that is good. The whole knowledge of the Law, is in the knowledge of our three-folde eſtate. 1. Of that we had by Creation 2 Of that wee haue now by Nature. 3. Of that wee ought to be now: this one end, to <hi>Depart from Iniquitie,</hi> is <hi>Finis vltimis,</hi> alwayes at the ende of all of them three. Wee are told what we were by Creation; that we ſhould ſtriue by <hi>Departing from iniquitie,</hi> to recouer our primitiue condition. Wee are ſhewed what wee are now by corruption; that wee might runne from the Law, to Chriſt; and lead a holy conuerſation. 3. Laſtly, it leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth vs what wee ought to bee; namely, Conformable to our firſt Image, of <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse and holineſse,</hi> by renouncing all Wickedneſſe. This is the onely Tribute ſiluer he requireth at our handes, as <hi>Moſes</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177637:35"/>thus expreſly telleth vs in <hi>Deuteronomie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 10.12.</note> 
                  <hi>What doth the Lord thy God require of thee; but to feare the Lord thy God, and to walke in his wayes?</hi> The ſame is the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Law of the Goſpell, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by <hi>Zacharie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 1.75.</note> 
                  <hi>That wee being deliuered out of the hands of our enimies, might ſerue him without feare, in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe before him, all the dayes of our life:</hi> as by <hi>Paul</hi> in like manner where he ſayth:
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>The Grace of God that bringeth ſaluation to all men, hath appeared, and teacheth vs, that we ſhould denie all vngodlineſſe, and worldly luſts; &amp; that we ſhould liue ſoberly, and righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent world, looking for that bleſſed hope, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of that glorie of that mightie God, and of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who gaue himſelfe for vs, that he might redeeme vs from all iniquitie, and purge vs to be a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people vnto himſelfe, zelous of Good workes.</hi> The like reſpect there is of all the Workes of God, and his Sonne Chriſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready wrought, or to be wrought for vs. The ſcope at which they driue, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation of our Sinnes.</p>
               <p>All the Workes of God, whatſoeuer they bee, muſt be of theſe three kindes. 1. Such
<pb facs="tcp:177637:36"/>as concerne our Creation, Preſeruation, Protection. 2. Or ſuch as belong to our Redemption by Chriſt. 3. Or ſuch as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to our communicate Redemption and Grace.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Creation of the World was for mans ſake, to the end that man might know God, and by knowing, glorifie him. This is plaine by this the Apoſtle ſayth:
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>The inuiſible thinges of him, that is, his eternall power, and Godhead, are ſeene by the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, being conſidered in his workes, to the intent that they ſhould be without excuſe: Becauſe that when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neyther were thankfull.</hi> Now God can not otherwiſe be glorified, but by our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the Law, by our departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; by our duties of pietie and integritie. No other end hee propoſeth to himſelfe in his afflicted puniſhments, that ſo they might conſider his anger towards ſinne, to be ſhie thereof, and ſhunne it. He hath determined the Diuels, and the Reprobates, to damnation, to no other ende, then to warne the Elect not to ſinne, and if they ſin, to ſaue themſelues by repentance, and by perfourmance, of future obedience. The patience of God, is to the ſame purpoſe:
<pb facs="tcp:177637:36"/>His ſufferance,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> is only a ſummons to our conuerſion, to which end ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>Deſpiceſt thou the riches of his bountifulnes, and patience, and long ſufferance, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the bountifulneſse of God leadeth thee to repentance?</hi> The common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie benefites of God, redound vnto the wicked. The Cloudes droppe downe Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vppon their Cloddes, they haue the gracious dew of his bleſsing, though none of his inheritance: That his practiſe might be preſident, and Patterne to vs, of pietie and perfection, as he intimateth in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion thereof, in this ſentence of moniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Bee yee alſo perfect, as your heauenly Father is perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 All the Workes of our Redemption, are of reference vnto this, <hi>Our departure from Iniquitie.</hi> For all the Promiſes of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in Chriſt, are to diſpell Deſpaire, that we ſhould not as abſorpt of Deſperation, plunge our ſelues through our ſinnes, into the pitte of Perdition: but contrariwiſe, vnder hope of Grace, ſhould repent vs of our Treſpaſſes, and depart from our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities. Chriſt, the Argument of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, conformed himſelfe to the rites of the Law, could defie euery aduerſarie that could accuſe him of Sinne, was obedient to his Father to the death; that his example,
<pb facs="tcp:177637:37"/>ſhould be our imitation, according to this his direction in ſuch cauſes; <hi>I haue giuen you an exſample, that as I haue done, ſo ſhould yee doe. Hee that ſaith hee is in him, muſt walke as hee hath walked.</hi> Hee cured the Sicke, raiſed the Dead, filled the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie with good thinges, as for other ends, ſo namely and mainely, for this one ende, that while they recounted how Sinne brought theſe euils into the World, they ſhould ſhake off theſe euils, and forſake their ſinnes; the Caution giuen by Chriſt to the Palſey-man: <hi>Now thou art whole, ſinne no more, leaſt a greater euill come vnto thee.</hi> Hee remitted ſinnes, that wee ſhould committe no more ſinnes, wherefore hee ſayeth to the adultreſſe in the Ghoſpell: <hi>Jf no man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee, J doe not condemne thee, Goe in peace.</hi> The ſame matter of meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ariſeth vnto vs, out of the circumſtances of his paſſion. Hee did beare the Croſſe, and ſuffered the ſhame for vs, to deliuer vs determined to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death; and to leaue vs an example, that it ſeeme not grieuous vnto vs, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all manner of euill vniuſtly for his ſake This vſe Saint <hi>Peter</hi> giueth vs of Chriſte Paſsion for vs:
<note place="margin">1. Pet 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Foraſmuch as Christ hat ſuffered for vs in the fleſh; arme your ſelues like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe with the ſame minde, which is, that hee the hath ſuffered in the fleſh, hath ceaſed from ſinne that he hence forward ſhould liue, not after the
<pb facs="tcp:177637:37"/>luſtes of men, but after the will of God:</hi> That is in a word, as it is elſe where deliuered, <hi>That wee ſhould crucifie the fleſh with the luſtes thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He prayed for his Enimies, to teach vs to forbeare vengeaunce, &amp; to beare wronges with patience.</p>
               <p>Hee dieth, not onely to ſaue our Soules from death: but alſo to the end, that wee ſhould die to our ſinnes. The application that <hi>Paul</hi> maketh of that Article of the Fayth. He is buried,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> that wee alſo ſhould burie our ſinnes, and roule a great Stone ouer the Graue of them, that they neuer riſe againe. The inference,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> the ſame Apoſtle maketh in the ſame place: <hi>Wee are buried then with him by baptiſme into his death, that like as Chriſt was rayſed vp from the dead to the glory of the Father: ſo wee alſo ſhould walke in newneſſe of life.</hi> Hee diſpatcheth his Apoſtles into the wide perambulation of the world, with this legatiue Commiſson, to preach the Goſpell, and Remiſsion of ſinnes; and to this ſpeciall end, that wee ſhould make an end of ſin, as in the clauſe of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, is not obſcurely intimated, where theſe wordes are added; <hi>Teaching them to obſerue ſuch thinges, as J haue commaunded you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee aſcended vp to Heauen, not onely to appeare for vs in the preſence of God, but
<pb facs="tcp:177637:38"/>alſo to raiſe vp our Soules from the nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Pitte to the vppermoſt Heauens, that wee might learne in liew of this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, to lead an heauenly life. It is the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that <hi>Paul</hi> giueth vs out of the ſayd Learning:
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>If yee be then riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe thinges that are aboue, and not thoſe thinges that are on the earth.</hi> This was <hi>Paules</hi> courſe of conuerſation; <hi>Our conuerſation is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, foretelling the finall Iudgement, hee inſerteth this ſpeciall end hereof, to giue to euery one according to his workes. Wherefore it ſtandeth vs in hand as much as our Soules &amp; Bodies are worth, to looke to our wayes, and to follow our iniquities no more.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Laſtly, the workes of our communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Redemption, implye the ſame conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Apoſtle ſhutteth them all vp in foure wordes.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Predeſtination.</hi> 2. <hi>Vocation.</hi> 3. <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 4. <hi>Glorification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The intention of our <hi>Election,</hi> heedeth this condition, as where <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth it, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee hath choſen vs in him before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy and without blame before him in loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of our <hi>Vocation,</hi> wee may ſay the like: For God hath not created vs to vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but vnto holineſſe. Wee haue Fayth
<pb facs="tcp:177637:38"/>giuen vs to obey his Call: Firſt, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we might pertake of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt imputed to vs. 2. Next, that wee might obſerue the Law; and that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Law might be fulfilled in vs.
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.19.</note> Hence commeth in this Interrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle: <hi>Doe wee make the Law of none effect through Fayth? God forbid: yea, wee eſtabliſh the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee <hi>Iuſtifieth</hi> vs, in pardoning our ſinnes, that we ſhould be no more factiue inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to ſinne,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> but that we ſhould <hi>Giue vp our members as ſeruantes vnto righteouſneſse in holineſse:</hi> he inſtilleth his holy Spirit into vs, that being made the Members of Chriſt, and the Temples of the holy Ghoſt, wee ſhould take heed how hereafter we pollute and defile our bodyes with iniquities. It is the quicke expoſtulation and queſtion of the bleſſed Apoſtle:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Know yee not that your bodyes are the Temples of the holy Ghost? Hee that ſhall pollute the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy.</hi> All the Religion that we haue in the Church; as Preaching, Sacraments, Prayers, Diſcipline, driue at this end; to die to ſinne, to liue to God.</p>
               <p>To conclude, our <hi>Glorification</hi> includeth &amp; concludeth the ſame conſideration; <hi>Then ſhall God be all in all,</hi> becauſe then there ſhall be no more ſinne to ſtriue againſt God.
<pb facs="tcp:177637:39"/>Wherefore, bend wee, and band wee all our Sinnewes and Sides againſt the ſides of Sinne, that wee may liue in his feare, and die in his fauour; and enioy that Place, which the Father of old hath prepared, Chriſt of late hath purchaſed, and to which wee are ſealed, by the Spirit of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: To theſe three Perſons, and one God, be praiſe, and glorie, now and euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177637:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
